How is it possible that Africa, with so
much wealth beneath its soil, such a
generous natural resources, and an
abundance of water and sunlight, remains
the poorest continent in the world?
In July 2023,
that rhetorical question was posed in
St. Petersburg by Captain Ibrahim
Traoré, then just 35 years old and 10
months into his rule of Burkina Faso.
It was meant to justify his country's
pivot toward Russia and its increasingly
confrontational break with Europe.
In the space of only a few years, three
Sahelian states, Mali, Burkina Faso, and
Niger, expelled French troops, rejected
the existing regional order, and
proclaimed the restoration of their
sovereignty. They were supposed to
finally defeat terrorism on their own, a
threat the West had spent a decade
failing to bring under control.
And so the French were replaced by the
Russians. First, Wagner mercenaries,
then the Kremlin-controlled Africa
Corps. The result?
Today, jihadist groups are seizing ever
more territory. The juntas control less
and less of their own countries, while
Russian forces are suffering their
heaviest losses in Africa since Moscow
began expanding across the continent. At
the same time, gold mined under Russian
protection is being routed through the
Middle East on to global markets,
helping finance the Kremlin's war
machine.